Curious how AI coding agents can speed up your data science workflow in VS Code?
Today, I'll show you step by step how to use the HVE Extension's RPI workflow, research,
planning, and implementation on the Titanic data set, even if you've never used AI agents before.
Let's start by installing the HVE extension, which powers the RPI workflow.
Open VS Code and look for the extensions icon, four squares in the left sidebar.
Click it and in the search bar at the top, type HVE Core. Choose the HVE Core extension from the list
and click the blue install button. Once it's finished, you'll see a confirmation on the right
and new agents become available in your co-pilot chat panel.
This process is quick and doesn't require any extra setup.
As a data scientist, getting these tools installed lets you work smarter, with research,
planning, and code generation all in one place. Next, let's explore the Titanic data using
At-Task Researcher. Click the co-pilot chat panel, it looks like a speech bubble in the sidebar.
In the Agent Picker at the top, select At-Task Researcher. Type your request,
explore Titanic.csv, summarize columns, and give key insights for data science.
Hit enter. The agent researches your data set and creates markdown notes showing data types,
missing values, and basic stats. Check the explorer on the left. You'll see a new folder,
dot dot dot, co-pilot tracking, with a research summary in markdown.
This step gives you quick, organized insights, much like how you would sketch out an initial
EDA, but faster and automated. With research in hand, let's plan our analysis using At-Task Planner.
In co-pilot chat, switch the Agent Picker to At-Task Planner. Type, plan a data science workflow to
load Titanic.csv, explore it, and build a simple model predicting survival.
Send your prompt. The agent creates a step-by-step plan in markdown,
typically outlining data loading, EDA, pre-processing, model training, and evaluation.
Now check the explorer. Under dot co-pilot tracking, there's a new planning file.
Open and review these steps. You'll see a practical workflow similar to what you draft for a basic
ML task, saved and structured automatically for you. Finally, let's turn your plan into
working code using At-Task Implementer. Switch to this agent in co-pilot chat.
Prompt, write Python code to load Titanic.csv, explore the data, and build a simple logistic
regression predicting survived. The agent generates a Python script, usually named something like
explore Titanic.py, covering data loading, basic EDA, and the model. Check the explorer for this
new file, open it, and review the generated code. Let's run it. Open the terminal panel
at the bottom of VS Code. Type Python explore Titanic.py and hit Enter. The script outputs basic
stats and a model score. No copy-paste needed. This step shows how HVE can save you time
by automating code creation for real data workflows. If you want the shortcut version,
HVE offers the at-rpi agent that handles research, planning, and implementation in one go.
In co-pilot chat, select at-rpi agent, prompt, build a Python workflow for Titanic survival
prediction. You'll get research, plan, and code together. Best for quick tasks. But for
learning the process, stepping through the three agents gives you more control and transparency.
We just walked through the RPI workflow using HVE in VS Code, from installing the extension
to researching, planning, and implementing a Titanic data science project with AI coding agents.
You've seen each step, including the shortcut at RPI agent for fast results. Ready to try this RPI
workflow yourself? Install HVE core in VS Code, open your Titanic data set, and let the AI agents
accelerate your next project. Happy coding!