Ever wondered how to supercharge your data science workflow with AI agents directly in VS Code?
Today, I'll walk you through installing the Hyper Velocity Engineering Extension
and using its AI native agents to load, explore, and model the Titanic data set
without writing any code yourself. Let's start by installing the Hyper Velocity Engineering,
or HVE extension in VS Code. Click the extensions icon on the left sidebar. It looks like four squares.
In the search bar that pops up, type Hyper Velocity Engineering. When you see it in the list,
click the blue install button. That's it. No need for any API keys or credentials.
Now, let's explore the agents HVE adds to VS Code. Click the co-pilot chat icon.
It looks like a speech bubble in the sidebar. A chat panel will open.
In the agent picker at the top, you'll notice several agent options,
including at-task researcher, at-task planner, and at-task implementer. These are your AI partners
for end-to-end data science tasks. We'll use them step by step to work with the Titanic data.
First, let's research the Titanic data set. In the co-pilot chat panel,
select at-task researcher from the agent picker. Type explore-titanic.csv and summarize the data.
Hit enter. The agent will create a research markdown file. To see the output, look in the explorer.
You'll find a new .co-pilot tracking slash research folder with a markdown file inside.
Open it to review the automated analysis. Next, let's plan the actual analysis.
In the co-pilot chat panel, switch to at-task planner.
Type plan a Python script to load, explore, and predict survival on Titanic.csv.
The planner agent will create a plan file in the .co-pilot tracking plans folder.
Check the explorer for this new plan. Open it to read through the detailed steps
the agent has devised for our data science workflow.
It's time to bring it all together. Select at-task implementer in the co-pilot chat agent picker.
Prompt it. Implement the plan for titanic.csv analysis in Python.
The agent generates the complete script. No copy pasting required.
Check the .co-pilot tracking details folder for the implementation details file.
Open the file to see the ready to run Python code.
Double-click the script to open it in the editor.
Then click the run Python file button at the top right of the editor.
The terminal will display the output, likely some basic EDA and survival predictions using the Titanic
data. This all happens automatically thanks to HVE's agent workflow.
We installed HVE core, explored its agents, and walked step by step through researching,
planning, and implementing a data science workflow on the Titanic dataset.
All seamlessly inside VS code using AI agents.
Try out the hyper-velocity engineering extension in your own projects
and experiment with the other agents like at-rpi agent to speed up more complex workflows.